<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An ordinance presented to the Honourable house of Commons, by Mr. Bacon, a lawyer in Suffolk, and Mr. Taet, both of the Members of the same House, and by their meanes was twice read, and referred to a committee. : Pretended for preventing, growing and spreading of heresies. With some briefe observations thereupon, shewing how contrary it is to that law of love, which teacheth men to doe to others, as they would have others doe to them.</title>
            <author>Bacon, Nathaniel, 1593-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B01694</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B356</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201099</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">49520837</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 49520837</idno>
            <idno type="VID">174081</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B01694)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 174081)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2662:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An ordinance presented to the Honourable house of Commons, by Mr. Bacon, a lawyer in Suffolk, and Mr. Taet, both of the Members of the same House, and by their meanes was twice read, and referred to a committee. : Pretended for preventing, growing and spreading of heresies. With some briefe observations thereupon, shewing how contrary it is to that law of love, which teacheth men to doe to others, as they would have others doe to them.</title>
                  <author>Bacon, Nathaniel, 1593-1660.</author>
                  <author>Taet, Mr.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year. 1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print bleed-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Persecution --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Heresies, Christian --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Liberty of conscience --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:174081:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 1 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:174081:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 1 -->
            <p>AN ORDINANCE PRESENTED TO THE Honourable houſe of Commons, by Mr. <hi>Bacon,</hi> a Lawyer in Suffolke, and Mr. <hi>Taet,</hi> both of them Members of the ſame Houſe, and by their meanes was twice read, and referred to a COMMITTEE.</p>
            <p>Pretended for preventing, growing, and ſpreading of Hereſies.</p>
            <p>VVith ſome briefe Obſervations thereupon, ſhewing how contrary it is to that Law of Love, which teacheth men to doe to others, as they would have others doe to them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year. 1646.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:174081:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 2 -->
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:174081:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 3 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:174081:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 3 -->
            <head>An Ordinance preſented to the hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Houſe of Commons, by Mr. <hi>Bacon,</hi> a Lawyer in Suffolk, and Mr. <hi>Taet,</hi> both of them Members of the ſame Houſe, and by their means was twice read, and referred to a Committee.</head>
            <p>BE it ordained, that all ſuch as ſhall from and after the date hereof, willingly preach, teach, print, or write, publiſh and maintaine, any ſuch opinion contrary to the Doctrines enſuing;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Viz.</hi> That God is preſent in all Places, That God is, or that he is One in three Perſons, Or doth know or fore-know all things; Or that he is Almighty, Or that he is perfectly Holy, Or that he is Eternall. Or that ſhall in like manner publiſh, That Chriſt is not God coequall with the Father; Or ſhall deny the Manhood of Chriſt, Or that the Godhead and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of Chriſt are ſeverall Natures, Or that the Manhood of Chriſt, is pure, unſpotted of ſin; Or that ſhall publiſh, that Chriſt did not die, or roſe from the dead; nor is aſcended into Heaven bodily, Or that his death is meritorious in behalfe of Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers. Or that ſhall publiſh or maintaine, as aforeſaid, that Chriſt is not the Son of God, Or that the Holy
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:174081:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 4 -->Ghoſt is not God, Or that the Scriptures are not the Word of God, Or that the Bodies of Men ſhall not riſe after they be dead, Or that there is no day of judgement after death.</p>
            <p>Such publiſhing with obſtinacie, ſhall be judged Felony: Such perſons ſhall by two witneſſes be bound over by two Juſtices unto the Gaol-delivery, and the Delinquent ſhall be indicted for Felony; and upon finding the ſame indictment, and that the party be found guilty, and ſhall not abjure his ſaid error, he ſhall ſuffer the pairs of death, without benefit of Clergy: But upon abjuring of the ſaid error, he ſhall upon two ſufficient Sureties be bailed.</p>
            <p>And be it further ordained, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat if after abjuring the ſaid errours, he ſhall publiſh it again, he ſhall be indicted and put to death.</p>
            <p>And be it further ordered, that if any perſon ſhall wittingly and preſumptuouſly, or contrary to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, blaſpheme the name of God, or any of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Trinity, or ſhall impugne the word of God, ſuch offences ſhall be adjudged Felony, and the Offender committed without Bayle or Mainprize; and the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie being found guilty, ſhall be branded in the left Check, with the Letter <hi>B.</hi> and upon the like offence the ſecond time ſhall ſuffer death.</p>
            <p>And be it further ordained, that all perſons who ſhall publiſh any of the ſeverall errours hereafter en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing, <hi>viz</hi> That all men ſhall be ſaved; that a man by nature hath free will to turne to God; That God may be worſhipt by Pictures or Images; or that the ſoule of any man after death goes neither to Heaven nor Hell, but to Purgatory; or that the ſoule of man
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:174081:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 4 -->dyes or ſleeps when the body is dead; or that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations or workings of the Spirit, are a rule for a Chriſtians life; though divers from, or contrary to <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he written Word of God; or that a man is bound to believe no more then by his reaſon he can compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend; or that the Morall Law contained in the Ten Commandements, is no rule of a Chriſtians life; or that God ſees no ſinne in the juſtified; or that a Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver need not repent nor pray for the pardon of ſin; or <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat the two Sacraments of Baptiſme; and the Lords Supper, are not Ordinances commanded by the Word of God; or that the Baptizing of Infants is unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; or that ſuch Baptizing is void, and of none effect; or that ſuch perſons are to be Baptized again: and in purſuance thereof, ſhall baptize any perſon formerly baptized: or that the obſervation of the Lords Day, as it is injoyned by the Ordinances and Lawes of this Realm, is not according, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Word of God, or that it is not lawfull to <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yn in publique, or Family Prayer, or to teach Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to pray; Or that the Churches of England are <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot true Churches; Or that the Miniſters or Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, are not true Miniſters or Ordinances, Or that the Church government by Presbyterie, is Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ian, or unlawfull; or that the Magiſtracy, or power of the Civill Magiſtrate by law eſtabliſhed in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> is unlawfull; or that all the uſe of Armes for Publique defence (be the cauſe never ſo juſt) is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull.</p>
            <p>And in caſe the party ſo accuſed for any of the ſaid <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rrours, be committed before two Juſtices, the party <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> committed ſhall be ordered to renounce his ſaid
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:174081:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->errour in the publique Congregation of the Pariſh Church whence the complaint comes; and in caſe he refuſes or neglects the ſame at or upon the day, time, and place appointed by the ſaid Juſtices, that he ſhall be committed to priſon by the ſaid Juſtices, untill he ſhall find two Sureties, of Subſidie men that he ſhall not publiſh or maintaine the ſaid errour or errours any more.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Some briefe Obſervations upon the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Ordinance.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THat Mr. <hi>Taet</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bacon</hi> be deſired to offer to the conſideration of the Honorable Houſe, ſeriouſly to debate, how far their power can extend (as to the knowledge or worſhipping of God) over the perſons and Conſciences of the people who in truſt them.</p>
               <p>For how can there be an intruſting power of any thing, from any or many men, to the cuſtody or orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of any compacted body, but only ſuch power which evidently appeareth to reſide in every Individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all part thereof in themſelves.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Mr. <hi>Taet</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bacon</hi> ſhould doe well firſt to prove, that any individuall part of this Parliamant, or people, of any Nation, injoyes ſuch a power in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, either to direct or compell their owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, in the knowledge or worſhip<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of their Creator<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which as yet is not evident, for</p>
               <p>It is Impoſſible that any finite creature can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend an Infinite incomprehenſible God, for it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by many texts of Scripture to be the only act of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:174081:5"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->Love, that dwels with God to regulate and guide the hearts of men, according to his owne good pleaſure; who requireth no man to adore him in knowledge or worſhip, more or leſſe, but as every man is fally per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded in his own mind.</p>
               <p>For man in himſelfe hath no kdowledge of God, But as God manifeſteth himſelfe unto him, therefore man of neceſſity muſt follow in practice the dictates thereof, otherwiſe man ſinneth againſt the light of knowledge, whereby his condition is more abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable then the brute Beaſt that periſheth.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That Mr. <hi>Taet</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bacon</hi> notwithſtanding, they have done in this the Clergies worke, will now at laſt move the Honorable Houſe to remember how odious and abominable former Acts of Parliaments in ſuch caſes hath proved in the ſight of this generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſome Parliaments eſtabliſhing that Idoll of pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, requiring conformity thereunto, under the paines of Death, affirming it to be agreeable to the Word of God. Other Parliaments condemns this way as Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian; and eſtabliſheth Epiſcopacy, alledging that agreeable to the mind of God, with the uſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer, Surplices, and other devices, requiring obedience thereunto, under the like pains and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. So that many for adhering to their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſuffered Death, for pretended Hereſies and errours: which pretended errors ſince appeareth to be truth, and the guilt of their blood remains on this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at this day, and had not ſuch men out-went the limitation of Parliaments, we might have ſate in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe till this time. That this Parliament hath decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Epiſcopall government to be Antichriſtian, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:174081:6"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->ſetled Presbyterie in ſtead thereof, but the Prieſts not contented therewith, without a ſole power of Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction over the lives and conſciences of the people of this nation, indevoreth to inſlave all inquiring people to ſeeke knowledge from their lips, to believe as they believe, to know no more then they judge fit we ſhould know.</p>
               <p>The contrary minded ſhall be inflicted with impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, and death, under pretence of Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie and errours, when there is no ſuch thing can be brought forth by the contrivers thereof, much like the old Religion in <hi>Henry</hi> the eights time, hanging in <hi>Smithfeild</hi> a Proteſtant on one day for his judgement, and a Papiſt the next for his; to ſuch a condition are we like to be reduced through the inſtigation of the Clergie of our times, whoſe end is their intereſt and domination over us the free people of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FJNIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
